(61) 99164-3843 Brasília, DF cayanportela@hotmail.com

Cayan Portela

Data Scientist

GitHub: cayan-portela LinkedIn: cayan-portela

With over 5 years of experience in data science, statistics and quantitative finance, working in medium and large companies. Experience in analyzing structured and unstructured data and solving business problems using data-driven techniques. Acting in process improvement, which results in task optimization, cost reduction and increased productivity.

SKILLS

Tools and Languages Quantitative Research R, Python, SAS, SQL, Git, ET_FX, MarkDown

Machine Learning, Statistical Modeling, Probability

Communication English, C2 (EF SET 78/100)

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist / Investment Division

2019 - current

Brasília

Bank of Brazil

• Development of churn models, identifying customers with probability of evasion.

- Risk sensitivity analysis in investors portfolios.
- Automation of simulation models, providing pessimistic and optimistic scenarios forecasts.
- Implementation of external information via API and web-scrapping.

Volunteer professor

2019 — current

Brasília

Universidade de Brasília, UnB

- Contemporary Topics in Finance Data Science.
- Quantitative Methods and Models for Decision Making (2019/1).

Statistician / Innovation, Regulation, Infrastructure and Credit Studies

Institute of Applied Economic Research, IPEA

2017 — current

Brasília

Brasília

- Econometric and quasi-experimental models for causal effect.
- Supervised and unsupervised machine learning methods.
- Analysis of financial system indicators.
- Data visualization (interactive and static) and external data collection.

Data scientist / Researcher

2017 - current

Machine Learning Laboratory in Finance and Organizations

- Consulting for interactive data visualization panel development.
- Delivering courses focused on data science and statistical computing.

Unprecedented studies and research using machine learning applications.

EDUCATION

Phd candidate, Finance and Quantitative Methods, University of Brasília Msc, Experimental Statistics, University of São Paulo Bachelor, Statistics, Universiyt of Brasília

Current

2015

PUBLICATIONS

Feature selection and deep neural networks for stock price direction forecasting using technical analysis indicators Machine Learning with Applications, 100060, (2021)

Application of Machine Learning Ensemble Techniques in the Banking Industry

CFA Society Brazil, Honorable mention (2020)

The robot from Ipanema goes working: estimating the probability of jobs automation in Brazil

Latin American Business Review, 20.3, (2019)

Probability of automation of Brazilian occupations and Industry 4.0

https://lamfo.shinyapps.io/automacao

Published at Folha de São Paulo, Época Negócios and others.

2018